It can be intimidating to take your first step into foreign cinema
對很多人而言，要看懂外國電影並不容易
Language barriers
語言屏障
And cultural barriers
文化差異
But if you are a cinephile
然而，如果你是一位電影迷
You probably knows more about Asian cinema than you think
那麼，你對亞洲的文化其實早有一定認知
Because a lot of your favorite Hollywood movies...
因為許多為人鍾愛的好萊塢電影裡
have elements inspired by Eastern culture
都能找到一些亞洲文化
Some more obvious and others
有時甚至十分明顯
Here is an ode to Asian culture in Western made movies
在這部視頻裡，我們將讚頌一下西方電影裡的亞洲文化
"I know Kung-fu"
“我學會功夫了”
Well, you are in the wrong place for that.
兄弟，來錯地方了
Anyway, I want to talk about THIS
好吧，我想說的是這個
You may already know about wire-fu
“吊威亞”一詞，大家應該不陌生
a technique originated in Hong Kong
源於香港，港片當中十分常見
It's basically actors being pulled by invisible wires
說白了就是隱形鋼絲吊演員
Popularized by The Matrix in the West
由《廿二世紀殺人網絡》帶入西方電影后
it has since been used in many Hollywood movies
許多好萊塢電影也可是使用這個技巧
What you may not know is that this visual has more cultural significance than just flying
但你也許不知道，吊威亞背後其實有更深的文化背景
How'd you do that?
怎麼做到的？
The air
空氣
You can't see it but it feels your lungs
無色無形，但注滿心肺
You treat the air the same way
你要待空氣如凡物
You step on it as you with a stone
踏氣如踏石
You swim through it as you with the sea
泳氣如泳海
And all you have to do is believe
只要全心全意相信自己
It's called "qing gong",
這叫做“輕功”
Literally means the technique to be light
也就是讓自己變輕的功夫
It's a martial technique for scaling obstacles
現實中是一種用來跨越障礙物的武術技巧
And in Chinese martial art novels
中國武俠小說中
This technique has been greatly exaggerated
這個技巧被各種誇大
to a point where characters can jump on water
乃至角色可以踏水而飛
or even control their own body weight
或輕於鴻毛
Explanations for this technique differs
技巧背後的原理眾說紛紜
One version says these martial artists can control an unseen life force called "qi"
其中有說俠客們可以操控一種叫做“氣”的無形力量
Qi...
氣
Internal energy
內在能量
The essence of life
生命之源
By manipulating this force in and around them
通過控制體內和四周的氣
the martial artists can be lighter than air
俠客們能變得比空氣還輕
and gracefully float around like dragonflies
如蜻蜓點水般飛行
After the release of The Matrix
《廿二世紀殺人網絡》發行之後
the visual of Qing Gong continues to evolve
輕功的銀幕形象繼續演變
The film you are watching here is called Hero
畫面上的這部電影叫做《英雄》
Director Zhang Yimou takes inspirations from religious wall paintings
導演張藝謀向宗教壁畫取得靈感
his characters in Hero fly and glide like the gods and goddesses of China
他的角色如中國神明一般優雅飛翔
If you are fan of The Matrix for its kick-ass action
如果你十分喜歡《廿二世紀殺人網絡》的動作場面
and philosophical stories
和充滿哲學的劇情
Then maybe you should give Hero a watch
《英雄》或能對上你的偏好
"The force is what gives a Jedi his power"
“原力是絕地武士的力量來源”
"It's an energy field created by all living things"
“所有的生物都散發著原力力場”
"It surrounds us and penetrates us"
“原力包圍我們，穿透我們”
"It binds the galaxy together"
“將整個銀河系維繫在一起”
Didn't we just talk about this?
我們不是剛說過這個嗎？
It's no secret the Star Wars takes a lot of inspiration from Asian culture
大家都知道《星球大戰》背後有很多源於亞洲的文化基因
the force is pretty much just qi
原力就是氣
Instead of lifting a user,  it lifts other things
雖然不能自己飛，但可以讓其他物體飛起
And the lightsaber...
而光劍
Katana in space
太空武士刀
The connections between Star Wars and Eastern culture are numerous
《星球大戰》和東方文化的有著千絲萬縷的聯繫
From the visual design
從視覺設計
To the fighting
到動作設計
To the philosophy behind the iconic weapon
到系列標誌性武器背後的則學
"This is the weapon of a Jedi Knight"
“這是絕地武士的武器”
In Chinese culture swords are considered a gentlemen's weapon
在中國文化中，劍是君子的武器
"An elegant weapon from the more civilized days"
“是一種文明時期的優雅武器“
Because it demands skill rather than strength
因為劍不論蠻力論技巧
"That lightsaber was Luke's and his father's before him"
”這把光劍是天行者和他父親的“
"and now it calls to you"
”現在它在呼喚你了“
Recognizing the owner by the sword
以劍認主
And the one swing one kill fighting also draws parallel with katana combat
一刀一殺的動作場面也和武士電影十分相似
After Star Wars and Kurosawa
在《星球大戰》和黑澤明的作品問世之後
Japanese sword movies continue to evolve
日本刀劍電影繼續進步著
One of my favorite, surprisingly, is an adaptation to manga
我最喜歡的，意外地，是一部漫畫真人化作品
Rurouni Kenshin
《浪客劍心》
It's a film about reformed assassin with a sword that doesn't kill
電影講述一名洗心革面後的刺客
who must find his own way to protect the people around him
以一把不能殺人的刀保護他人的故事
If you want some amazing sword fights
如果你對刀劍武打有興趣
Or are into the mystics of swords
或對劍背後的哲學文化有興趣
Rurouni Kenshin comes highly recommended
《浪客劍心》是一部不可錯過的作品
See the similarity?
是不是很像呢？
This is called "battojutsu"
這叫拔刀術
The sword drawing technique
又叫居合術
Basically quick draw for swords
和西方的快槍手十分相似
The origin of the technique is convoluted
拔刀術的起源不明
One version says it was technique used by samurai to counter assassination attempts
有傳是武士對抗刺客的防守技巧
That's not to say Western quick-draw is inspired by battojutsu
當然，這並不是說西方電影的快槍起源於拔刀術
Here's Shane doing it, before Kurosawa
《原野奇俠》的快槍便早於黑澤明的《椿三十郎》
But with Kurosawa's love for western movies
但黑澤明鍾愛西部電影
And Sergio Leone's love for Kurosawa
而賽爾喬·萊翁內對黑澤明又十分喜愛
it's safe to say these two genres influenced each other
可以說，這牛仔電影和武士電影互相影響了不少
and the parallels are uncanny
乃至兩者幾乎同步
The intense stares
緊張的對視
The fast and accurate kills
快狠準的殺戮
And of course... putting a weapon back
當然，還有把武器放回去的的過程
Much like qing gong
跟輕功一樣
the art of battojutsu gets more exaggerated over time
拔刀術隨著時代改變而被誇大化
In popular media, you can often see the objects being cut remains one piece
流行作品中，經常會見到刀客把刀收回之後
until the sword is put away
被斬的物品才斷開
As if reality is too slow for the swordsman
彷彿現實世界的反應比刀客慢
The film you're watching right now is called Zatoichi
屏幕上的電影叫做《座頭市》
It's one of the longest-running film series ever
是世界上最長的電影系列之一
And it's still going on to this day
直到今天，《座頭市》依然偶有新作品
The titular blind swordsman was THE folk hero in the mind of a generation
座頭市這位盲人刀客，曾是一代人心目中的英雄
Much like the Clint Eastwood cowboy
跟奇連·伊士活的牛仔一樣
If you want to  see some good action in a western-style folktale
你若想要看一部充滿動作場面的民間故事電影
Zatoichi is a great choice
《座頭市》是一部上乘之選
I suggest the 17th entry: Zatoichi Challenged
我推薦第十七作：《座頭市：血煙街道》
Anyway, this is called "dim mak"
咳，這叫“點脈”
Not that one
不是這個……
Remember the concept of qi?
還記得“氣”嗎？
In Chinese fiction, by interrupting the flow of qi in someone
中國文學中，通過打斷對方的氣
You can paralyze them
你可以麻痺對方
and it can be done with finger injecting qi as well
俠客甚至可以用手指注入氣的方式來打斷
You can also reverse it by restoring the flow
也可以重新打通穴道而解穴
It's acupuncture, but with the force
其實就是針灸，但用氣不用針
The extreme version of it can cause someone to die
練的極致甚至可以一拳打死人
and is referred to as death touch
也就是傳說中的“打死穴”
The "five point palm exploding heart technique" from Kill Bill
《標殺令》中的“五點破心擊”
originated from a movie that features the original Pai Mei
來源於一部白眉道人的電影
But not used by Pai Mei
但它並非白眉道人的絕招
At least not in the original Chinese version
至少在中文版中並不是
In Clan of the White Lotus, the technique is called "hundred steps soul reaping palm"
在《洪文定三破白蓮教》中，這個攻擊叫做“百步追魂掌”
And it's used by Bak Nin, who belongs to the same clan as Pai Mei
是白眉道人師弟，百年道人的絕招
When struck by this technique the victim dies within 100 steps
被此招擊中後，傷者會在百步以內
due to the qi being shut down
氣絕身亡
In recent years though
然而現代電影中
with Chinese audience wanting more realism in movies
中國觀眾偏好真實一點的電影
Dim Mak no longer shows up in movies as often
點脈很少再出現在銀幕上
and if it does, it's for comedic effect
就算出現，也只是一個搞笑的存在
But if you don't mind your classic style martial flicks with some comedy in it
但你若不介意武俠電影中出現一些搞笑段子
Fong Sai-yuk I and II are two movies to watch out for
《方世玉》和《方世玉2》是兩部不錯的作品
Featuring the titular folk hero of China, played by Jet Li
講述由李連杰扮演的民間英雄方世玉的故事
It's an amazing blend of old-school action from the Shaw brothers era
這部電影混合了紹氏電影時期的武打
and the more up-to-date story and visual of the Jackie Chan era
和成龍電影時期的畫面和故事
So that is some of the gateway films for you to get into Asian cinema
希望這些電影能讓你對亞洲電影產生興趣
And some background explanations to help you understand them better
也希望這些信息能讓觀看亞洲電影變得輕鬆一些
But if you've still find these concepts overwhelming
但如果你依然覺得這些文化概念太難理解
Well, maybe let yourself get confused
那就讓自己迷茫地觀看吧
It's like going on a vacation
就當作是一場旅遊
Where's the fun, if you already know everything about it?
有未知，才有意思，不是嗎？